<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>David Sheeren on David Sheeren</title>
    <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in David Sheeren on David Sheeren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for papers - Special Issue in Remote Sensing Journal</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_si_rs_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_si_rs_2020/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34;  href=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/biodiversity_mapping_monitoring_horizontal_dark-banner%201.png&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/biodiversity_mapping_monitoring_horizontal_dark-banner%201.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Colleagues,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Special Issue &lt;strong&gt;Remote Sensing for Biodiversity Mapping and Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; aims to publish original research that specifically addresses various aspects of biodiversity mapping and monitoring over space and time using remote sensing from local to global scales. We invite a wide range of contributions from methodological to applied and multidisciplinary research about the following (non-exclusive) topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taxonomic, structural, and functional diversity mapping from RS data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Species distribution modeling based on RS data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retrieving biophysical and biochemical variables from RS data and radiative transfer models;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessing and predicting ecosystem services from RS data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ecosystems health monitoring from RS data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reconstructing ecosystem trajectories over time from RS data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced machine learning techniques (deep learning, transfer learning, active learning) for biodiversity mapping based on RS data;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fusion of multimodal images (optical/thermal/radar/lidar) to improve biodiversity mapping and monitoring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviews covering one or more topics are welcome.
We encourage the authors to make their sample data and computational tools publicly available through online resources to ensure the reproducibility and transparency of all the experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deadline&lt;/strong&gt; for manuscript submissions: 30 November 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. David Sheeren
Dr. Jean-Baptiste Féret
Dr. Laurence Hubert-Moy
Dr. Sophie Fabre
(Guest Editors)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/journal/remotesensing/special_issues/biodiversity_mapping_monitoring&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI &lt;em&gt;Remote Sensing&lt;/em&gt; Journal website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Stability and Spatial Instability in Mapping Forest Tree Species by Comparing 9 Years of Satellite Image Time Series</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/karasiak_rs_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/karasiak_rs_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our collective book about Geographic Data Imperfection is out!</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/book_imperections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/book_imperections/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34;  href=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/book_imperfection.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/book_imperfection.jpg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://gdr-magis.imag.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GdR CNRS MAGIS&lt;/a&gt; working group about &lt;a href=&#34;http://gdr-magis.imag.fr/actions-prospectives/incertitude-epistemique-des-donnees-aux-modeles-en-geomatique/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;spatial uncertainty&lt;/a&gt; has published a new book called &lt;strong&gt;Geographic Data Imperfection 1: From Theory to Applications&lt;/strong&gt;, Batton-Hubert M., Desjardin E. and Pinet, F. (Eds).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About this book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Geomatics is a field of science that has been intimately intertwined with our daily lives for almost 30 years, to the point where we often forget all the challenges it entails. Who does not have a navigation application on their phone or regularly engage with geolocated data? What is more, in the coming decades, the accumulation of geo-referenced data is expected to increase significantly.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Table of Contents is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/book/10.1002/9781119507284&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wiley website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Un regard sur l&#39;évolution de la géomatique : analyse de 4 décennies de recherches au sein du Département de Géographie de l&#39;Université de Liège</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/billen_bsglg_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/billen_bsglg_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A conceptual framework for the governance of multiple ecosystem services in agricultural landscapes</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/vialatte_le_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/vialatte_le_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Object-based fusion for urban tree species classification from hyperspectral, panchromatic and nDSM data</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/aval_ijrs_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/aval_ijrs_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Generic Framework for Combining Multiple Segmentations in Geographic Object-Based Image Analysis</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/lefevre_ijgi_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/lefevre_ijgi_2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7th French Hyperspectral Remote Sensing Symposium (SFPT-GH)</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_sfpt_gh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_sfpt_gh/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34;  href=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/flyer_sfpt_gh.png&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/flyer_sfpt_gh.png&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next &lt;strong&gt;SFPT-GH symposium&lt;/strong&gt; on hyperspectral imagery will be held on 9-10 July 2019 in Toulouse. This conference is organized by ONERA/DOTA, IRIT/ENSEEIHT, DYNAFOR/ENSAT and INRA. The aim of this symposium is to bring together all the french scientists involved in hyperspectral image processing on various application domains: geology, planetology, vegetation, atmosphere, coast and urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deadline for abstract submission is &lt;strong&gt;March 11, 2019&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will have the pleasure to invite &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lx.it.pt/~jun/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Professor Jun Li&lt;/a&gt; from the Sun Yat-Sen University, School of Geography and Planning (China) as a keynote speaker for a presentation about &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Recent Advances in Spectral-Spatial Hyperspectral Image Classfication&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the details are available on the website: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sfpt-gh2019.onera.fr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://sfpt-gh2019.onera.fr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Red Oak...</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/sentinelhub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/sentinelhub/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34;  href=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/Sentinel-2_L2A-timelapse_CheneR_2018.gif&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/Sentinel-2_L2A-timelapse_CheneR_2018.gif&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an excerpt of Sentinel-2 time series acquired over the year 2018 showing forest stands of conifer and deciduous species near Toulouse, France. If you watch the timelaps until the end, Red Oak will be unmasked&amp;hellip; Take a look at your forests with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sentinel-hub.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sentinel-hub EO Browser&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DYNAFOR is 15 years old!</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/dynaforbirthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/dynaforbirthday/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34;  href=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/15ans_Dynafor.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://dsheeren.github.io/img/posts/15ans_Dynafor.jpg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent a nice meeting last tuesday with all members of DYNAFOR to celebrate the fifteenth anniversary of the laboratory. G. Balent, the lab&amp;rsquo;s founder (recently retired!), started the meeting with a presentation about the genesis of the group and the research questions associated at startup in 2003. M. Deconchat, our last director, made a quick review of our activities conducted for 15 years. We finished the morning meeting by a SWOT analysis (Strengths, Weaknesses, Opportunities and Threats) to prepare the next years. After lunch, an &amp;ldquo;agri-escape ecolo-game&amp;rdquo; was organized at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/lafermedumatet&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ferme du Matet&lt;/a&gt; by Lucie and Virgine (two past PhD students). Finally, the day ended at the village of St André with our local partners and farmers around our exhibition and drinks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back from ForestSAT&#39;2018, Univ. of Maryland, USA</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/forestsat2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/forestsat2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://forestsat2018.forestsat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://forestsat2018.forestsat.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/logo-color-ctr-650b.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://forestsat2018.forestsat.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ForestSAT&amp;rsquo;2018 Conference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was organized by the University of Maryland and the NASA Goddar Space Flight Center at USA, Washington D.C. during 5 days (1-5 October 2018). Many of us from DYNAFOR, CESBIO and ONERA Toulouse were there. The program of the conference was really exciting with talks on all the subjects: large area mapping, forest structure and biomass, forest biodiversity assessment, forest composition and phenology, change detection and disturbances, forest in the global carbon cycle&amp;hellip; with optical time series, LiDAR, UAV, SAR data. It provided us a good overview of the current research works on this topic. It was also the opportunity to meet other scientists and present our lastest works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oral presentation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Karasiak N., &lt;strong&gt;Sheeren&lt;/strong&gt; D., Dejoux J.F., Féret J.B., Willm J., Monteil C., Is ground-based phenology of deciduous tree species consistent with the temporal pattern observed from Sentinel-2 time series?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herrault P.-A., Thierion V. and &lt;strong&gt;Sheeren&lt;/strong&gt; D., Using the new French Land Cover Map (OSO) as spatial inputs in forest ecological modeling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheeren&lt;/strong&gt; D., Thierion V. and Herrault P.-A., Quality assessment of MODIS Vegetation Continuous Fields of Tree Cover over France.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aval J., Fabre S., Zenou E., &lt;strong&gt;Sheeren&lt;/strong&gt; D., Fauvel M. and Briottet X., An ensemble classifier approach for urban tree species classification from ground-based spectral references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detection of individual trees in urban alignment from airborne data and contextual information: a marked point process approach</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/aval_isprsj_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/aval_isprsj_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New published paper in Remote Sensing Journal</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/paperrs2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/paperrs2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper named &lt;strong&gt;Spatial and Temporal Dependency of NDVI Satellite Imagery in Predicting Bird Diversity over France&lt;/strong&gt; (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/10/7/1136&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;publication&lt;/a&gt;) intended to confirm the conclusions we obtained in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1470160X14000818?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous study&lt;/a&gt; made in southwestern France. Here, we used a large bird dataset collected at the French national scale to (i) compare single date NDVI data and DHI (i.e. the Dynamic Habitat Index) to explain and predict species richness patterns of different bird groups; (ii) identify the best NDVI acquisition date to explain and predict bird species richness; and (iii) test whether the best NDVI acquisition date depends on the dominant land cover in landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observed that continuous (unclassified) predictors derived from satellite imagery contribute to build efficient Species Distribution Models (SDM) at large spatial scale. However, because of temporal variability of remotely sensed predictors over the year, acquisition time periods of the data affect the models’ performance. We found that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compared to a combination of multiple NDVI time periods or to the components of DHI, performance of bird models is higher with single time period of NDVI variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Models’ performance is time and context-dependent. At the French scale, end summer (NDVI 14-Sep) and begin of autumn (NDVI 30-Sep) are in most cases, the best time periods to explain and predict woodland and farmland birds species richness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best time period of NDVI is the one that better reflect dominant habitats in the bird survey plots.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Habitat components at finer scale have to be combined with climate variables at macro scale to explain and predict patterns of habitat specialist species.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest that the most powerful approach is the simplest one. Only one image of appropriate time period is required for mapping bird species richness. This makes the use of unclassified remotely sensed data very operational for bird monitoring programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/10/7/1136&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://res.mdpi.com/def5020035eabd603ef29ea6366e32135bd59807fa334a9299c18427598207369505029f840fcf0bdc235a41f05982e60768c48811f655564d76aa2139bb4313e7544ab37ee561595fc712bdcc496aee21974e90b748f4115b4c406526f061032b9de04b59f9603a4dd2f4b819a7c858a36f71ba41b6b65a3ab57d674de5e5fc9c4848478c2aee78fabfe3a369ade8552f5b56720ea78ae77f085c5b922f6d6ed9d6ba9230a06e183937696d2d0ff64ed3e860&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial and Temporal Dependency of NDVI Satellite Imagery in Predicting Bird Diversity over France</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/bonthoux_rs_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/bonthoux_rs_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of spatial and temporal discontinuities of forest habitats on the current presence of flightless saproxylic beetles</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/cateau_plos_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/publication/cateau_plos_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
