<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on David Sheeren</title>
    <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on David Sheeren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dsheeren.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>IGARSS&#39;2021 Symposium in Brussels!</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/igarss2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/igarss2021/</guid>
      <description>Save the date! The next IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium IGARSS&amp;rsquo;2021 will be in Brussels (Belgium) from the 11th of July to the 16th. The symposium is organized by Belgium (UCL, VUB, U Ghent) and Dutch Universities (TU Delft, Univ. Twente, WUR) with BELSPO, VITO and RMA. A great opportunity to go back at home ;-)!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for papers - Special Issue in Remote Sensing Journal</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_si_rs_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_si_rs_2020/</guid>
      <description>Dear Colleagues,
This Special Issue Remote Sensing for Biodiversity Mapping and Monitoring aims to publish original research that specifically addresses various aspects of biodiversity mapping and monitoring over space and time using remote sensing from local to global scales. We invite a wide range of contributions from methodological to applied and multidisciplinary research about the following (non-exclusive) topics:
 Taxonomic, structural, and functional diversity mapping from RS data; Species distribution modeling based on RS data; Retrieving biophysical and biochemical variables from RS data and radiative transfer models; Assessing and predicting ecosystem services from RS data; Ecosystems health monitoring from RS data; Reconstructing ecosystem trajectories over time from RS data; Advanced machine learning techniques (deep learning, transfer learning, active learning) for biodiversity mapping based on RS data; Fusion of multimodal images (optical/thermal/radar/lidar) to improve biodiversity mapping and monitoring.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our collective book about Geographic Data Imperfection is out!</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/book_imperections/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/book_imperections/</guid>
      <description>The GdR CNRS MAGIS working group about spatial uncertainty has published a new book called Geographic Data Imperfection 1: From Theory to Applications, Batton-Hubert M., Desjardin E. and Pinet, F. (Eds).
About this book
&amp;ldquo;Geomatics is a field of science that has been intimately intertwined with our daily lives for almost 30 years, to the point where we often forget all the challenges it entails. Who does not have a navigation application on their phone or regularly engage with geolocated data?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7th French Hyperspectral Remote Sensing Symposium (SFPT-GH)</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_sfpt_gh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/call_sfpt_gh/</guid>
      <description>The next SFPT-GH symposium on hyperspectral imagery will be held on 9-10 July 2019 in Toulouse. This conference is organized by ONERA/DOTA, IRIT/ENSEEIHT, DYNAFOR/ENSAT and INRA. The aim of this symposium is to bring together all the french scientists involved in hyperspectral image processing on various application domains: geology, planetology, vegetation, atmosphere, coast and urban areas.
The deadline for abstract submission is March 11, 2019.
We will have the pleasure to invite Professor Jun Li from the Sun Yat-Sen University, School of Geography and Planning (China) as a keynote speaker for a presentation about &amp;ldquo;Recent Advances in Spectral-Spatial Hyperspectral Image Classfication&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Red Oak...</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/sentinelhub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/sentinelhub/</guid>
      <description>Here is an excerpt of Sentinel-2 time series acquired over the year 2018 showing forest stands of conifer and deciduous species near Toulouse, France. If you watch the timelaps until the end, Red Oak will be unmasked&amp;hellip; Take a look at your forests with Sentinel-hub EO Browser!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DYNAFOR is 15 years old!</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/dynaforbirthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/dynaforbirthday/</guid>
      <description>We spent a nice meeting last tuesday with all members of DYNAFOR to celebrate the fifteenth anniversary of the laboratory. G. Balent, the lab&amp;rsquo;s founder (recently retired!), started the meeting with a presentation about the genesis of the group and the research questions associated at startup in 2003. M. Deconchat, our last director, made a quick review of our activities conducted for 15 years. We finished the morning meeting by a SWOT analysis (Strengths, Weaknesses, Opportunities and Threats) to prepare the next years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back from ForestSAT&#39;2018, Univ. of Maryland, USA</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/forestsat2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/forestsat2018/</guid>
      <description>The ForestSAT&amp;rsquo;2018 Conference was organized by the University of Maryland and the NASA Goddar Space Flight Center at USA, Washington D.C. during 5 days (1-5 October 2018). Many of us from DYNAFOR, CESBIO and ONERA Toulouse were there. The program of the conference was really exciting with talks on all the subjects: large area mapping, forest structure and biomass, forest biodiversity assessment, forest composition and phenology, change detection and disturbances, forest in the global carbon cycle&amp;hellip; with optical time series, LiDAR, UAV, SAR data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New published paper in Remote Sensing Journal</title>
      <link>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/paperrs2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dsheeren.github.io/post/paperrs2018/</guid>
      <description>This paper named Spatial and Temporal Dependency of NDVI Satellite Imagery in Predicting Bird Diversity over France (see publication) intended to confirm the conclusions we obtained in a previous study made in southwestern France. Here, we used a large bird dataset collected at the French national scale to (i) compare single date NDVI data and DHI (i.e. the Dynamic Habitat Index) to explain and predict species richness patterns of different bird groups; (ii) identify the best NDVI acquisition date to explain and predict bird species richness; and (iii) test whether the best NDVI acquisition date depends on the dominant land cover in landscapes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>